Diogo**Pina**

Full-Stack Software Engineer

Contact

diogojpina@gmail.com diogojpina.github.io +55 11 96646-5557 (whatsapp) GMT -3

Languages

english (advanced) portuguese (native) spanish (basic)

Programming

♥NodeJS

♥React
TypeScript
PHP
HTML & CSS
Others
React Native
Python
Angular
Java, C/C++
Database
MySQL, MariaDB,

PostgreSQL,

MongoDB,

Firebase

Knowledge

Agile: XP, Scrum,
Kanban, Lean
Machine Learning
DevOps
Continuous Integration
Continuous Delivering

Summary

I am a remote full-stack software engineer specialist in web development and I have over 10 years of experience in software development using Javascript stack (NodeJS + React) and PHP. Besides that, I have database servers, GIT, and a mobile development background. I have knowledge and experience in project management in technology using Agile, such as XP, Scrum, Kanban, and Lean.

I am also a Ph.D. Candidate in Computer Science at the University of São Paulo. My research is in software engineering and focuses on technical debt prioritization. The main goal is to develop context-adaptive methods using machine learning approaches to prioritize the payment of technical debt items in real software projects.

Education

2023 (expected) Ph.D. in Computer Science
São Paulo University, Institute of Mathematics and Statistics (IME-USP)

MSc in Computer Science
São Paulo University, Institute of Mathematics and Statistics (IME-USP)

Measuring Technical Debt São Paulo University, Institute of Mathematics and Statistics (IME-USP)

Bachelors in Computer Science

Technical Debt Overview

São Paulo University, Institute of Mathematics and Statistics (IME-USP)

Professional Experience

Since 09-2020 iRemedy Development of an e-commerce platform and automation process using NodeJS and React.

Full-Stack

Since 01-2014 Remote Software Engineer Full-Stack

O7-2009/12-2013Agência Weber Consultant and remote full-stack software engineer Consultant and cons

Software development leader. 01-2007/07-2009Inglês 200 horas

Inglês 200 horas Full-Stack Web Developer

Development of interactive e-learning platform to English courses.

01-2006/01-2007**PWI**Computer To

7**PWI**Computer Technician
Technical support on Linux servers and development of maintenance scripts.

Academic Experience

since 2019 **Visiting Researcher**

Prioritizing Technical Debt

University of Maryland, Baltimore County (UMBC), Department of Information

Systems

01-2019/02-2019 Teacher of Summer Course

IME-USP

Introduction to Web Systems Development with PHP

08-2018/12-2018Professor Internship

IME-USP

Extreme Programming Laboratory Course

08-2017/12-2017Professor Internship

IME-USP

Extreme Programming Laboratory Course

02-2017/07-2017 Professor Internship

IME-USP

Mobile Computing Course

08-2015/12-2015Professor Internship

IME-USP

Extreme Programming Laboratory Course

02-2015/07-2015Professor Internship

IME-USP

Mobile Computing Course

08-2014/12-2014Professor Internship

IME-USP

Work in

Programming Laboratory II Course

Publications

Since 2018 Prioritizing Technical Debt - An Machine Learning Approach

Progress

A case study on Apache projects to develop and evaluate the accuracy of a technical debt prioritization method based on machine learning approach.

Since 2018 A Mapping Study on Prioritizing Technical Debt Work in Progress

A systematic mapping study was performed to identify and analyze the main papers on technical debt prioritization, covering the main computer science bases, such as ACM DL, IEEE Xplore, Science Direct, Scopus, Springer Link and Web of Science.

05-2017 Effects of Technical Debt Awareness: A Classroom Study International

Conference on Agile Software Development

Technical Debt is a metaphor that has, in recent years, helped developers to think about and to monitor software quality. The metaphor refers to flaws in software that may affect future maintenance and evolution. We conducted an empirical study in an academic environment, with nine teams of graduate and undergraduate students during two offerings of a laboratory course on Extreme Programming - XP Lab. The teams had a comprehensive lecture about several alternative ways to identify and manage Technical Debt. We monitored the teams, performed interviews, did close observations and collected feedback. The results show that the awareness of Technical Debt influences team behavior. Team members report thinking and discussing more about software quality after becoming aware of Technical Debt in their projects.